So now that we've learned about the time travel feature, let's talk about the retention time.
That means the time we can travel back into the past.
Here in Snowflake.
So this is depending on the edition you are using.
So if you are using the standard edition in Snowflake, you have the time travel capability for traveling
up to 24 hours back in the past.
So this is here for the standard edition for all of the other editions.
So starting with the Enterprise and Higher, we have this time travel feature available for up to 90
days.
But that does not mean now that we can always, for all objects by default, travel back for 90 days
because we have a so-called retention period.
So this is basically a property of our objects, for example, for a table.
And this is specifying for how much time we can travel back for this object.
So the default value here is usually set to one.
So if a table has this retention period property set to one, then we can travel back for 24 hours for
this table.
But in the at least enterprise and all of the other higher editions, we can change this retention period
value for up to 90 days.
So this is what we should know.
It's not really complicated and therefore, let's get hands on again and have a look into Snowflake,
how we can use and alter this retention period.
So let's first answer the question of how can we see this retention time property?
We can do this using the show tables command.
So this we can also filter using the like command and then see only the tables that have included in
their name these characters customers.
So in our case, we have two tables that fit this criterion.
So we have the customers and the customers wrong table.
And if we have a look in these properties, we find here this retention time property and this is exactly
this property that we are talking about.
So for both of these tables, as we have mentioned, these values are per default set to one.
So this is what we have learned also here in this lecture.
And that means that we can, for these two tables, travel back for one day.
That means for 24 hours.
So all changes that have occurred in the last 24 hours, we can travel back to and we can restore these
this data and how the data has looked here within this retention time period.
But now the question is how can we alter this value so we can do this using two methods?
So the first one would be if a table already exists, we can use the alter table command and then set
this property data retention time in days to a different value.
So for example, we could set this value to two, we execute this and then have a look at the tables
again.
And then we see that for this table that we have just altered here, this property, this is now set
to two.
The second method would be to, if we create this table, set this property to a certain value that
could be different from one, because as we said, the default is always that this value is set to one.
So if we create this table that is called read example retention time example, and we set this value
to three, let's have a look.
We can show the tables to see this table.
And in here we find this red example and this has a retention time of three.
So this is the second method of setting the retention time period if a table is not existing yet, but
we want to create it and then we can just pass here this property value while we create this table.
But now if we alter here this property to a value of zero, that would of course mean that we cannot
travel back in time at all.
We cannot use this time travel feature at all.
So now we have done this, and if we now drop this table, we can also not drop it because this time
travel period is set to zero and this dropping is also a component of the time travel.
So let's verify this.
If we drop this table and now we try to drop it, we get this error message that this table did not
exist or was purged.
That means that we cannot use this time travel at all for this table.
So this is just something that helps maybe in the understanding and that we should be aware of.
So to summarize things here, this is the retention time in days property that is set to one per default.
But we can alter this in our tables using here this alter command to just set this value to a different
value.
And then also we can here pass this property value.
If we create a table and set it to a certain value.
And this is specifying of how many days we can use the time travel feature.
But now the question might arise if we have the capability to travel back in time for 90 days, why
should we set this not to 90 days?
And why is the default then only one?
And the answer to this is that there is an indirect cost involved.
That means that we have a little bit more storage used because this time travel needs to be stored as
well and we have to pay for the storage.
So therefore in the next lecture, let's have a closer look on these costs that are related to the additional
storage through time travel.